Don't!
不要
Xu Fengnian doesn't deserve to die.
徐凤年不该死
You shouldn't be here.
你不该在这里
You know me, don't you?
你认识我
Your mother was the head of the 3,000 swordsmen of Chu.
你母亲是大楚三千剑侍之首
Of course, I've seen you.
我自然见过你
Lord of Jing'an used me as a pawn
靖安王把我当作棋子
and sent me to assassinate Xu Fengnian,
刺杀徐凤年
but Xu didn't kill me.
但是徐凤年并没有杀我
He's been really good to Her Grace.
他对殿下真的不错
He didn't deceive her.
并非欺瞒诓骗
If they hadn't spoken for you,
若不是两人都为你说话
you would have been dead.
你已经死了
Your Grace, you're still alive.
殿下还活着
It's a blessing for our country.
实在是天佑我大楚
My father asked Xu Xiao not to kill me.
是父皇求徐骁留我性命
Because of that,
就凭这一点
I'll spare Xu Xiao's life for one time.
我可以饶徐骁一次不死
If you're that good,
你真有这本事
why haven't you ever been to North Liang these years?
这些年怎么从没去过北椋
Avoid the solid and strike the weak.
兵者避实击虚
North Liang is dangerous. I won't go there recklessly.
北椋为凶地不可轻闯
But you broke into the palace.
你连皇宫都闯了
North Liang is more dangerous
北椋之险
than the palace of Liyang.
远胜离阳皇宫
Are you afraid of North Liang?
你怕北椋
If I had known Her Grace was in North Liang,
若知道殿下在北椋
I would have been there early.
我早就去了
Your Grace.
殿下
These years,
这些年
you've suffered a lot.
您受苦了
I'm fine, actually.
我其实还好
Your Grace, do you have anything to pack?
殿下看看还有什么要带走的
To pack?
带走
Why should I pack?
带去哪儿
I'm taking you back to Chu.
当然是随罪臣归楚啊
West Chu has long perished.
西楚早就灭国了
But we still have the people.
可楚人犹在
It isn't just you, is it?
这句话说的不只是你吧
Of course not.
当然
Not just me.
不仅仅是我
The survivors of Chu
大楚幸存之士
have gathered in Shu.
已然汇聚蜀地
Shu is in chaos now.
如今蜀地纷乱四起
All of the people are your subjects.
这些人都是您的臣民
They've been in despair.
他们绝望已久
They look forward to returning home with Your Grace.
他们在等公主带他们回家
No way!
不行
I won't let her go.
我不放人
I didn't ask you.
我没问你
She is mine!
她是我的
Nonsense.
谁是你的
Move.
让开
He wanted Jiang Ni and I stopped him.
他要姜泥我没让
I'll stop you, too.
换成是你也一样
No one can stop me
我曹长卿要带人走
if I decide to take her away.
天下谁能挡我
Snakes in Sleeves.
两袖青蛇
Li Chungang?
李淳罡
I know my name.
我知道自己叫什么名字
You needn't tell me.
不用你说
Weren't you left at Mansion of Lu?
您不是被留在卢家了吗
Did you think I was so gullible?
你以为我老人家那么容易被骗呢
Have you been with me all the time?
您一直都在
It was patchy at best
对上卢白颉那两刀
when you fought Lu Baijie.
马马虎虎有点样子
After that, it was unbearable to witness.
之后就乱七八糟了
Step aside.
待一边去
I'll talk with you later.
回头训你
Even Wang Xianzhi
今天就算是王仙芝亲临
can't stop me today.
也休想拦我
You're getting old.
你老了
Cut the nonsense!
说甚废话
Chess...
棋
Uncle Chess Master.
棋诏叔叔
Your Grace.
殿下
Would you please stop fighting?
能不能不要动手
I am
曹长卿
at your disposal.
听凭殿下吩咐
Uncle Chess Master.
棋诏叔叔
Can I stay here?
我能不跟你走吗
Your Grace.
公主殿下
If you stay,
如果您留下
you're a maid at best.
只能是一个侍女
Do you think he'll marry a maid?
这样的身份他会娶你吗
I don't want to marry him.
我没说要嫁他
Wait a minute.
等 等一下
Since there is no fight,
既然不打了
why don't we go inside
要不别站在这儿说
and have a good talk?
找个地方进屋说
All right.
也好
Qingniao,
青鸟
go to tell
你去外面
Grandpa Wei and Ning Emei
找魏爷爷和宁峨眉他们
to guard the temple.
让他们守住报国寺
Don't let anybody in.
不要让人进来
After I die,
我死之后
Your Highness, please let the little girl outside the temple go.
请世子放过寺外那个小丫头
Why would you die?
你为何会死啊
Cao Changqing showed up.
曹长卿现身
Shu will be in chaos.
蜀地乱局将起
I've heard all the big news.
天大的事情都被我听到了
Heaven will not tolerate it if I don't die.
我若不死天理难容
In fact, you have another choice.
其实你还有一个选择
If you go to North Liang,
如果你投入北椋麾下
you won't have to die.
就不用死了
If I go, the little girl
我若走了
will have no one to depend on.
就没人照顾了
Take her to North Liang.
把她一起带去北椋
Her paralyzed grandpa is seriously ill. He can't travel far.
她爷爷瘫痪加上重病无法远行
Before he passes away,
所以老人家去世之前
I can't leave Yangzhou.
我不能离开泱州
Don't worry.
没关系
Stay and take care of her.
你可以留下照顾她
Stay?
留下
Take it.
拿着
Use the money to treat her grandpa.
这些钱可以给老人治病
When he gets better,
等老人病好些
hire a carriage and take them to North Liang.
雇辆马车一起来北椋
Do you mean
你的意思是
I can leave?
让我走
There is no fight anymore.
没架打
You can't see the fun anyway.
你留着也没热闹看
Aren't you afraid I may leak the news?
你就不怕我传扬出去吗
If I want you to work for me,
我要用你
I must trust you.
就会信你
Chen Xiliang
陈锡亮
is at your disposal.
见过主公
My Lord, please wait for me.
请主公在北椋等我
No matter how long it takes,
不管多久
I'll wait for you.
北椋会等你
Do you think he can work for you?
觉得这书生可用
Yes.
可用
Aren't you afraid he'll betray you?
真不怕他卖了你啊
The circumstances of gentry and those of humble families
士族和寒门
are worlds apart in Yangzhou.
在泱州如天地之别
His only hope
他若想有希望
is to go to North Liang.
就只有到北椋去
If I made a bad decision,
哥哥若是踏入历史的泥泞
would you still follow me?
你愿意跟哥哥一起吗
(Baoguo Temple) As long as my grandpa is fine,
只要爷爷没事
I'll follow you wherever you go.
陈哥哥去哪我都陪着
That's a deal, then.
那我们就说定了
When your grandpa gets better,
等爷爷好起来
let's leave Jiangnan.
我们就离开江南
Where to go?
去哪呢
North.
往北去
Prime Minister.
见过宰辅
There you are.
你来了
You asked to see me.
宰辅相诏
How dare I not come?
岂敢不来
You're really enjoying this.
宰辅好享受啊
I don't like to build a reputation of honesty and poverty.
我不喜欢清贫养名那一套
I want all the scholars
我要让读书人看了
to envy me.
心生羡慕
Thus, it may arise
激发起
their ambitions to get promotions.
他们往上爬的愿景
Don't you agree?
不认同
I'm not in a position
这种事
to make comments.
我哪敢评论哪
I heard Cao Changqing showed up at Yangzhou.
我听说曹长卿出现在泱州
I heard that, too.
有这消息
The last time when people saw him,
最后见到
he seemed to head towards Yangcheng.
好像是往阳城去的
Is Xu Fengnian at Yangcheng, too?
徐凤年也在阳城
We can take advantage of it.
或许可以造势吧
We can spread the news
就说北椋
of North Liang and Cao Changqing...
和曹长卿他们
No.
不
Wait a bit longer.
再等等
Don't be anxious.
你那先别急
Let's see
看看
if Cao Changqing
曹长卿和徐凤年
will meet Xu Fengnian
会不会遇上
and
遇上了
what happens
又会是
when they meet.
什么状况
Yes.
好
Keep me posted
有消息
if there is any news.
尽快的送过来
Rest assured, Prime Minister.
宰辅放心
You can go.
去吧
You're really diligent
宰辅果然勤政啊
in handling official business at home.
把公务都拿到家里办了
Bringing the memorials back home
把奏章带回府
isn't appropriate, actually.
是不太合适
But to manage state affairs,
但为国理政
I can't attend to the trifles.
也顾不了这些琐碎的规矩了
People who make great achievements don't stick to small details.
成大事不拘小节
Prime Minister,
宰辅
you're with high ambitions.
好气魄啊
Righteous men of Chu
楚国义士
who are hidden in Shu
潜藏蜀地
have been expecting you for long.
苦等公主久矣
Xu Fengnian is very likely
徐凤年极有可能
to be the next lord of North Liang.
是下一任北椋王
The royal court of Liyang
离阳皇室
may give him a princess.
应该会送一个公主给他
Although North Liang is strong,
北椋虽强
it is subordinated to Liyang.
但终究臣属离阳
What does it have to do with Xu Family
姜泥走不走
whether Jiang Ni leaves or not?
跟徐家有什么关系
Your Grace,
公主
our people want you
若随我入蜀
to go with me to Shu.
便是民心所向
After we gather our troops,
待聚拢旧部
we can return to West Chu.
便可重归西楚
Liyang
而离阳
will have another enemy, then.
多一个外敌
North Liang's position
北椋地位
is more secure that way.
更加稳固
Besides,
其次
when you become the queen of Chu,
成了楚国女王
you'll be a fine match for Xu Fengnian.
你才能真正和徐凤年身份相当
I have nothing to do with him.
我和他什么关系都没有
Mr. Cao,
曹前辈
can I say something?
我能说两句吗
First,
第一
We won't let bandits have their own way
养寇自重的事
in order to distinguish ourselves.
我北椋不会做
Second,
第二
we keep the army ready for combat
北椋秣马厉兵
in order to bring peace to the world.
是为了守天下太平
We've never thought of rebellion
从没有想过叛乱谋逆
and starting a war again.
让刀兵再起
You're so pedantic and simple.
如此迂腐单纯
How can you be the Lord of North Liang?
怎么能做北椋王
There are enough big shots who have little regard
视人命如草芥的大人物
for human life.
已经够多了
I prefer to be a pedantic lord
我偏要做一个
with a bottom line.
有底线会迂腐的北椋王
What's your choice, Your Grace?
公主怎么选
I've never wanted to be a big shot.
我没想过做大人物
Not a big shot.
不是大人物
You're the last hope of our people.
您是西楚人最后的希望
Can you bear to see them being hopeless again?
公主忍心看楚人就此沉沦吗
Why must it be me?
为什么一定是我
Your blood
您身上流淌的血脉
brings you glory
为您带来荣耀
as well as responsibilities.
也生出责任
Your Grace,
公主
the royal family has no right to shirk their responsibilities.
王族无权逃避
Enough!
够了
Don't push her.
不要逼她
If you let Her Grace go with me,
世子若交还公主
I'll kill Chen Zhibao for you.
我可以替你杀陈芝豹
Jiang Ni isn't a bargaining chip.
姜泥不是筹码
No matter what you give me,
不管你给我什么
I won't trade her for it.
我都不换
You
你
want to force her to stay?
想强留公主
It's her fate.
她自己的命运
Let her make the choice.
让她自己选择
Have you thought about going home?
你想过回家吗
It's my dream to go home.
做梦都想
Since Chu perished,
楚国亡了
we've become
我们这些人
rootless duckweeds
就像浮萍断了根系
that have nothing to depend on.
从此无依无靠
We can't find a place to return.
再也寻不到归处
We don't know where to go.
也寻不到去路
If we reunite with the people of Chu,
若能与楚人重聚
we're not far from going home.
家乡也就不远了
But, Your Grace,
但是殿下
it's not important.
这不重要
What?
不重要
You have your own life.
你有你自己的人生
You don't owe us anything.
你不欠我们
You're not just the princess,
因为你不仅仅是公主殿下
you're also my friend.
你还是我的朋友
Your Grace,
公主
I respect your choice.
我尊重您的选择
I'm going with you.
我和你走
Jiang Ni!
姜泥
In fact, I'm used to being a maid,
其实我习惯了当一个侍女
reading books to make money.
每天读书赚钱
Spending several copper coins
几枚铜钱
on some rouge and powder would make me happy for a long time.
买些胭脂水粉我就能开心好久
Occasionally, I stole some cakes and pastries,
偶尔偷吃糕点
and you didn't find out.
也不会让你发现
Life is simple,
这样的生活很简单
but I like it.
可是我很喜欢
Then stay.
喜欢就留下
But Uncle Chess Master is right.
可是棋诏叔叔说得对
I have responsibilities.
我有我的责任
Too many people are expecting me.
太多人期待着我的出现
They're looking forward to the silver lining in darkness.
期盼着绝望里能看见光明
I've tasted despair.
我经历过绝望
I know how important
所以我知道这一点光明
the silver lining is to them.
对他们来说有多重要
I'm Jiang Ni.
我是姜泥
I'm your maid,
是你的侍女
but I'm also the princess of West Chu,
我也是西楚公主
a royal descendant.
王族血脉
Cao Changqing.
罪臣曹长卿
Yu Youwei.
民女鱼幼薇
Greetings, Your Grace!
拜见公主殿下
I'll give you my first order.
我的第一个命令
From now on,
就是你们二人
you needn't kneel to me.
以后见到我无需下跪
Your Grace.
公主
We mustn't neglect etiquette.
礼数不可废
Uncle Chess Master,
棋诏叔叔
are you going to disobey my orders?
你要抗命吗
I dare not.
罪臣不敢
Your Grace,
公主
let's set off now.
我们这就启程
I'll leave with you,
我会离开
but not now.
但不是现在
What do you mean?
殿下何意
Is the next stop after Jiangnan Mount Longhu?
江南下一站是龙虎山
Yes.
是
Except for Wudi City,
这次东行除了武帝城
the most dangerous place on the trip is Mount Longhu.
最危险的就是龙虎山了
I want to go with him first.
我想先与他同行
After we leave Mount Longhu,
等离开龙虎山
I'll go westward with you.
我就随棋诏叔叔西去
I'm not doing it for Xu Fengnian.
我不是为徐凤年
Xu Family saved my life.
徐家毕竟护我性命
I owed them.
这恩情该还他们
But, Your Grace,
但是殿下
we have two problems.
有两个问题
Please speak out.
棋诏叔叔请说
First,
第一条
since I've shown up,
我已然露面
you shouldn't travel
殿下就不可能再光明正大地
with Xu Fengnian openly,
和徐凤年同行
otherwise, people will think North Liang has allied with West Chu.
否则真成了北椋和西楚联手
The emperor of Liyang won't spare the Xu Family.
离阳皇帝不会放过徐家
Then I'll pretend to leave with you
那我假装和你离去
while going along with him in secret.
然后一路暗中随行
Sounds good.
也好
Second,
第二条
what should Xu Fengnian do?
这徐凤年怎么办
Harboring the princess of West Chu for so many years,
把西楚公主藏在身边这么多年
how does he explain to the royal court?
徐家怎么向皇室交代
Don't worry about that.
这倒不要紧
Over the years,
这么些年
I've been trying to assassinate Xu Fengnian.
我一直在尝试刺杀徐凤年
They can easily figure it out.
一查就能查到
Inferring from that, they'll make the conclusion
由此推断很容易得出
that I've been hiding my identity
我一直在隐藏身份
and trying to take revenge.
蓄意报仇的结论
Your Grace,
殿下
you've been trying to assassinate Xu Fengnian.
一直在刺杀徐凤年
Why?
为什么
Because...
因为
The life of the princess of Chu is useful.
楚国公主的命还是挺有用的
Of all people, why did they spare me?
为什么偏偏让我活着
At the crucial moment,
关键时刻
they can trade my life for something.
是拿我的命换东西
I thought Xu Xiao would kill me,
我以为徐骁会要我性命
so I've been trying to assassinate Xu Fengnian since I was a child.
所以从小就试着刺杀徐凤年
Granted that Xu Xiao harbored evil intent,
就算徐骁居心叵测
what did it have to do with you killing me?
跟你杀我有什么关系
Are all men fools?
男人都是笨蛋吗
It's obvious.
这还不明显啊
Jiang Ni knew she would die,
姜泥知道自己会死
so she kept trying to assassinate you
所以不停地刺杀你
in order to make you hate her.
是为了让你恨她怕她
She was afraid if she died in the future,
是担心将来自己有一天真死了
you might be sad.
你会难过啊
That was why you tried
你的刺杀从一开始
to assassinate me in the first place?
就是因此而起
Let's put that aside.
先不说这个
Another question is on my mind.
我刚才一直在想另一个问题
If Xu Xiao really wanted to kill me,
若徐骁真要对我不利
would he let me overhear it?
那他会这么凑巧让我偷听到吗
I don't think so.
我觉得不会
I don't, either.
我也觉得是
I think Xu Xiao
我觉得徐骁
let me overhear it on purpose.
是故意让我听到这些话的
And,
还有
I tried to assassinate him again and again.
我一次次刺杀他
Did it really escape Xu Xiao's notice?
真的能瞒过徐骁吗
Why didn't he stop me?
他为什么不阻止我
Do you remember your words?
你还记得你说的话吗
Xu Xiao often says he'll pay any price to achieve his goals.
徐骁常说为达目的不惜代价
I'm afraid you two are the price this time.
这一行你们二人恐怕就是代价
At first,
我一开始
I thought Xu Xiao would give you to the Lu family.
是以为徐骁会把你们交给卢家
Now I think about it,
可现在想想
Uncle Chess Master shows up,
棋诏叔叔出现
if we go with him,
如果我们跟他走了
the failed assassinations over the years
那这么多年的刺杀
happen to clear Xu Family of suspicion and hidden dangers.
就恰巧为徐家打消了猜疑和隐患
Is it just a coincidence?
有这么巧吗
Because of you,
因为有你们在
he didn't kill me.
所以刚才他没杀我
Yu Youwei and I play our real role
我和鱼幼薇真正的作用
here
其实是在这里
instead of Lu Family.
而不在卢家
Mr. Cao.
曹前辈
Yeah?
你为何会来阳城
I came for Her Grace.
我是为了殿下而来
How did you know Jiang Ni was with me?
你怎么知道姜泥在我身边
I didn't know if she was alive,
我不知道殿下是否还活着
but I found this.
但我找到了这个
- Divine Token?
神符
Yes.
对
It's the treasure of West Chu.
神符是西楚重宝
I found it in the hands of a vendor.
我在路边的商贩手里发现了它
Following the clue,
于是顺着线索
I came all the way here.
一路找到这里
Didn't you have the Divine Token?
神符不是在您手里吗
Someone borrowed it.
被人借走了
Who?
谁借的
His Lordship wants to borrow something from you.
王爷想借前辈一样东西
Grandpa Wei told you
魏爷爷跟您说
that Xu Xiao wanted to borrow the Divine Token?
是徐骁找您借神符
That's the reason
魏爷爷与我同行
why Grandpa Wei came with me.
原来是为了这一刻
Xu Xiao planned everything.
是徐骁设计一切
Today you'll be taken away.
今日之后你被带走
The princess of Chu reappears.
楚国公主再现
Liyang has another formidable enemy.
离阳再生大敌
North Liang's position will be more secure.
而北椋的地位就越发稳固
He didn't kick you out because your services were still needed.
飞鸟不尽 良弓不藏
Xu Xiao deliberately allowed Her Grace to assassinate you,
徐骁故意容忍公主刺杀
so that in the future,
就是为了以后
the whole world would know
让全天下都知道
Xu Fengnian resolved not to coexist with Her Grace.
徐凤年和公主誓不两立
In that case, the royal court would be more relieved.
如此一来皇室更加放心
The next lord of North Liang
这世袭罔替的北椋王
would be me for sure.
不给我还能给谁
All of these
这一切
were planned by Xu Xiao.
都在徐骁谋划之中
He has been scheming it since I was a child.
这布局甚至从小时候就开始了
Xu Xiao
徐骁啊
is a good player.
是个好棋手
Aren't you a matchless chess master?
你不是官子无敌 棋艺无双吗
How come you become
怎么这会儿
someone else's chess piece?
倒成了人家的棋子了
West Chu perished.
西楚覆灭
My last game
上一盘棋
came to a dead end.
已经走到绝路
Since then,
从那以后
I've never been a player again.
我就没有再做过棋手
Now I find Her Grace.
如今寻回公主殿下
We can start a new game.
重新开局
I'll challenge the heroes all over the world.
且看我与天下英雄试手
Your Grace.
殿下
It's time to go.
该走了
Let's fake
先造成
you being taken away by me.
您被我带走的假象
I'll leave after Mount Longhu.
龙虎山之后我才会真正离开
It seems suspicious
就这么走了
if we leave easily.
有点假
Come to the point.
想说什么就直说吧
I don't feel like guessing riddles.
我懒得猜你们话里藏话
Now that I've met God of Sword,
既然遇到剑神
how can I miss the chance of appreciating Snakes in Sleeves?
怎能不领教一番两袖青蛇呢
Snakes in Sleeves?
两袖青蛇
They're fighting.
动手了
Am I still alive?
我居然没死
Where is Cao Changqing?
曹长卿呢
He recognized
曹长卿
Jiang Ni, the princess of Chu,
认出姜泥是楚国公主
and became furious.
勃然大怒
Then he
对凤年
attacked Fengnian.
动手了
Fortunately, Mr. Li arrived in time.
幸好李前辈及时赶到
He exchanged one move with Cao Changqing.
与曹长卿交手一招
Who won?
谁胜谁败
It ended in a dead heat.
平分秋色
Cao took Jiang Ni and Yu Youwei away.
曹长卿把姜泥和鱼幼薇带走了
In order to protect Fengnian,
李前辈护住了凤年
Mr. Li didn't chase them.
不曾追赶
Indeed, she is the princess of Chu.
果然是楚国公主
Unfortunately, I didn't see them fighting.
可惜没看见曹长卿和剑神交手
Where is Fengnian?
世子人呢
He's in the yard.
就在院里
Mr. Lu, are you awake?
卢先生醒了
Did they only exchange one move?
他们仅仅只过了一招
Yes.
是啊
Only one move.
仅仅交手一招
It's like the immortals
天人临凡
coming to earth.
也不过如此了
Who would have thought
谁能想到
that a man could have such terrible power?
人能拥有如此可怕的力量
Now that you're awake,
卢先生既然醒了
do you still want to attack me?
还对我动手吗
Lu Family never wanted
卢家从来就没有想过
to break with North Liang.
要跟北椋决裂
What happened today,
今日之事
in the end,
说到底
is the result of her resentment.
都是她的怨恨所致
Fix all the blame on her?
一切都推给她
There must be someone that serves as a vent to your anger.
总要有人承受怒火
I'm not angry.
我没有怒火
She has the right to hate me.
她恨我是理所应当
It's not a capital offense.
算不上死罪
You're merciful.
世子宽仁
I admire that.
让人钦佩
My sister decides to stay.
我姐选择留下
If you don't want to break with us,
如果卢家不想和北椋决裂
please be kind to her.
请善待她
Rest assured.
世子放心
Let me walk you out.
我最后送你一程
I'm thinking about something.
我在想一件事
What is it?
什么事
Grandpa Wei borrowed Divine Token from Mr. Li,
魏爷爷从李前辈手里借走神符
but there must be another person
可把神符送到曹长卿眼前
who let Cao find it,
再制造线索
provided clues to him
让他自然而然找到报国寺的
and led him to Baoguo Temple.
应该另有其人
Grandpa Wei came to Jiangnan for the first time.
魏爷爷初到江南
He doesn't have anyone on hand.
并没有这样的手下
And?
还有呢
When Cao tried to attack me,
曹长卿现身时要对我动手
you were very calm.
我记得大姐始终面不改色
You knew Jiang Ni and Yu Youwei
你知道有姜泥和鱼幼薇在
wouldn't allow him to kill me.
曹长卿不会杀我
Even if Jiang Ni couldn't stop him,
就算姜泥拦不住他
you knew
你也清楚
that Mr. Li was here.
李前辈没有被骗
All changes today
今日一切变化
were within your expectation.
都在你预料之中
The whole scheme in Jiangnan
江南布局
was under your control.
是大姐掌控一切
I didn't get it all under control.
我并没有掌控一切
You being attacked by that woman
女刺客对你下手
was beyond my expectation.
就不在我预料之中
I was scared to death.
当时真的把我吓坏了
You knew Jiang Ni was Xu Xiao's pawn.
你知道姜泥是徐骁的棋子
He would give her to Cao.
是要送还给曹长卿的
I knew.
我知道
But you never told me.
可你一直没告诉我
Over the years,
这些年
I've been watching Jiang Ni and you.
我一直看着姜泥和你
Your second sister and I left North Liang one after another.
我和你二姐相继离开北椋
In a way,
从某种角度来说
it was Jiang Ni who had accompanied you till today.
是姜泥陪你走到了今天
Fengnian,
凤年
trust me.
相信大姐
Only in this way
只有这样
could Jiang Ni and you
你和姜泥的未来
have a future.
才有一线希望
Zhihu,
姐
you made a real effort to hide it from me.
你瞒得好辛苦
Though I'm in poor health,
姐虽然身体不好
I'm smart enough.
这儿可不输人
Listen to me.
听姐的话
Just leave.
安心走
Don't worry about me.
不要担心我
I'll be better than anyone else.
我会比任何人都过得好
Then,
然后
I'll wait for you to take me home.
等你来接姐回家
Grandpa Wei, you've got tricks.
魏爷爷好手段
I just followed orders.
只是领命行事
Please forgive me.
世子恕罪
Lady Zhihu.
小姐
They've gone.
走远了
Let's go inside and have a rest.
进去坐会儿吧
Lady Zhihu!
小姐
Be quiet.
别喊 别喊
Don't make him worry.
让他开心地离开
I'm afraid I can't live till we go home.
恐怕等不到回家了
Uncle, since you've made a scene,
棋诏叔叔刚刚出手
there must be a lot of people inquiring about the news today.
今日探听虚实的人必定不少
After tonight,
等过了今夜之后
I'll sneak back to join them.
我再偷偷回到车队里
Have you ever thought that
殿下有没有想过
if you were kept around Xu Fengnian
徐骁是故意把你
deliberately by Xu Xiao,
留在徐凤年身边
could your feelings to each other
你和徐凤年从小到大的羁绊
be real?
还能真吗
The heart won't tell lies.
可人心不会假
Just let me
就让我
accompany him to Mount Longhu.
陪他走完龙虎山这一程吧
Your Grace,
殿下
if Xu Fengnian is in danger,
如果徐凤年在龙虎山遇险
should I save him or not?
救还是不救
Why not?
为什么不救
If I save him,
如果我出手救他
it's like telling the world
就等于告诉全天下
that Xu Family and West Chu are not enemies.
徐家和西楚并非仇敌
At that time,
到那个时候
there will be no turning back for Xu Fengnian.
徐凤年可就没有退路了
Mr. Cao, you're highly skilled in martial arts.
曹先生武功高
You play chess well.
棋艺高
You're very learned.
学问也高
But you know little
就是对这女人吗
about women.
不太了解
Why do you say that?
何出此言
It's better if Xu Fengnian has no way back.
徐凤年没有退路才好啊
Her Grace can take him
到时候殿下就能把他
to West Chu, then.
一起带回西楚啦
- Uncle Chess Master. - Yeah?
棋诏叔叔
I want to eat cats.
我想吃猫
Why are you so cruel?
你不要这么残忍吧
Will you talk nonsense again?
还乱说话吗
I was telling the truth.
我说的都是实话
Watch your tongue from now on,
你以后说话小心点
or your cat may have bad luck.
不然你家猫后果可不好说
Can I talk secretly?
偷偷说两句行不行
You should pray I don't hear it.
最好别让我听见
Hey, wait for me.
你等等我呀
I'll go up and have a look.
我上去看一眼
All right, I know.
行了行了 我知道了
I won't let anyone assassinate him.
不能让人刺杀这小子
What have I done that I deserve this?
真不知道上辈子欠了谁的
Without Jiang Ni,
姜泥不在
His Highness becomes quieter.
世子沉默许多
Jiang Ni is a maid.
姜泥是侍女
You're a maid, too.
你也是侍女
Haven't you thought of replacing her?
你就没有想过取而代之
His Highness is the next lord of North Liang,
世子将来可是北椋之主
a powerful man in the world.
权倾一世呢
To escape the notice of the government,
为了躲避官府耳目
Jiang Ni won't come back tonight.
姜泥今晚不会回来了
I know.
我知道
Are you really going to let her go?
你真打算放她走啊
I can't defeat Cao Changqing.
我又打不过曹长卿
If you want her to stay,
你若想留她
I'll take care of Elegant Cao.
我来对付曹青衣
That girl is with extraordinary natural endowments.
那丫头资质超凡
She is suited for taking over the mantle of me.
适合传我衣钵
Then you should go to West Shu to take the apprentice.
那前辈可以到西蜀去收徒
Don't you want her to stay?
你真不想留她啊
I do.
想啊
But Jiang Ni is not just my maid.
但姜泥不只是我的侍女
She has her own way to go.
她有她自己想走的路
I can't keep everyone around
我不能把每个人
and not let them go.
都死拉在自己身边不放
It's not fair to them.
这对他们不公平
Fool.
蠢货
What a fool!
十足蠢货
Is it me?
我吗
Do you think it's me?
难道是我啊
I can't defeat you, anyway.
反正我也打不过前辈
Say whatever you want.
前辈说什么就是什么
I saw you using Snakes in Sleeves.
我看到你使两袖青蛇了
Was it okay?
还行吗
It was a complete mess.
一塌糊涂
It seems that I don't have natural endowments.
看来我资质一般
Why is it Snakes in Sleeves
为什么是两袖青蛇
instead of Dragons in Sleeves?
不是两袖青龙
Is there any hidden meaning?
这名字也有讲究
Flying snake turns into a dragon.
腾蛇化龙
Though dragon is noble and dignified,
龙虽然高贵威严
once a snake turns into a dragon,
可一旦变作龙
it becomes a beast
也就成了传说中
that serves immortals and gods.
仙人诸神的麾下走兽
It becomes their mount.
仙家坐骑
Only the snake that hasn't turned into a dragon
只有未化龙的蛇
harbors the ambition of breaking through all obstacles
心中才有斩破一切的野望
and the arrogance
才有往上攀爬
of climbing up and conquering the world
哪怕是和自己争斗
even if it must fight against itself!
也要吞噬天下的狂妄
Only by remembering the true meaning of the move
记住青蛇真意
can you master it.
才能用出真正的两袖青蛇
If you give in,
人若是屈服
you'll lose the unruliness.
就失去了这份不羁
Give in to whom?
向谁屈服
To your true heart.
向自己的心
People will be afraid.
人会害怕
They will despair,
会绝望
fear
会恐惧
or shrink back.
会退缩
All of those torture you from inside
你心里面的种种折磨牵扯着你
and stop you from moving forward.
不让你往前行
The real Snakes in Sleeves
真正的两袖青蛇
cuts off the knot in your heart.
是斩心之剑
Only by getting rid of your fear
斩断心中的恐惧
can you break through all shackles
才能踏破束缚
and go your own way.
去走自己选的路
Neither the swordplay nor the move or the meaning is important.
剑术剑招剑意都不重要
Understanding this
明白这些
helps you to master the move of Snakes in Sleeves.
才是两袖青蛇
(To the Son of Lord of North Liang) If I want to control a man,
要想让人被我的功法所控制
the most important thing
最重要的
is to disturb his mind.
就是乱其心神
Wu Su
这吴素
(Biography of Wu Su) was Xu Fengnian's beloved mother.
在徐凤年心中弥足珍贵
Through the images,
通过图形
we can affect his moods.
影响人的内心情绪
The dragon
这图中的天龙
will cut off his inner reliance on her.
会斩去他心底的依靠
In other words,
换句话说
I'll let Wu Su
我要让吴素
die once again in front of him.
在他眼前再死一遍
And maybe,
说不好
he'll become a lunatic.
他还会变成一个疯子
A lunatic
一个废了的徐凤年
becomes the next lord of North Liang.
成为北椋下一代主人
Isn't it the best result
这对皇族来说
for the royal family?
不是最好的结果吗
I'm going to ask His Highness to come down and have a rest.
我去接世子下来休息
General.
报告将军
We found a box near the camp.
在营边捡到一盒子
There is a note on it
上面贴了纸条
saying it's dedicated to His Highness.
说是献给世子
It's light.
很轻
It doesn't look dangerous.
不像有机关
What's wrong?
怎么了
It's about the night
是王妃
when Her Grace was ambushed in the capital.
京城遇伏那一夜的消息
I think we haven't found
不是这么多年
any clues over the years, right?
一直都没有查到蛛丝马迹吗
We must ask His Highness to see it first.
必须先让世子过目
Guard the camp and don't let anyone come up close.
你守住营地别让任何人接近
Yes.
好
Keep on the alert.
加强戒备
Yes!
是
Don't worry.
别担心了
There is no poison on that book.
那册子上没撒毒
Without tricks or poison,
既没机关又没下毒
how can a book
一本册子
hurt people?
还能害得了人吗
Some of your words I understand
我有些明白
while some I don't.
又有些不明白
What don't you understand?
哪些不明白
I don't understand
我不明白的是
how you cut off the knot in your heart.
心怎么斩
After all, the move of Snakes in Sleeves is just sword energy.
两袖青蛇说到底不过是剑气
How could it cut off the knot in your heart?
斩内心根本做不到啊
You can't really stab yourself in the heart, can you?
总不能真对着自己心口来一刀
Back in the day,
当年
I was bothered by the same question for a long time.
这也是困扰了我很久的问题
After I invented Snakes in Sleeves,
我创两袖青蛇之后
I was almost unrivaled in the world.
纵横天下难逢敌手了
Since then,
自此起
I've got the name of God of Sword.
便有了剑神之名
Extraordinary.
了不起
But deep down inside,
可我心底
I was anxious and confused.
始终焦躁困扰
I was struggling
苦苦挣扎
to find a way out.
难寻出路啊
Why?
为什么
Because my move
因为我的两袖青蛇
needed unyielding wild snakes.
是不屈野性之蛇
But humans have the nature of being slack
可人性总有懈怠
and compromising.
有妥协
One day,
如果有一天
if I lost the unyielding spirit,
我失去了这份不屈之心
my swordplay
我的剑道
would come to a dead end.
也就走到了末路
So I was afraid and lost.
所以我害怕
It was like the dead end had already come to me.
仿佛绝路就在眼前
I couldn't escape from it.
我却躲不开也避不掉
I knew the dead end
我知道这绝路
came from the fear in my heart.
来自于我内心的恐惧
Only by breaking the misty barrier deep down inside me
只有斩开心底迷障
could I move forward.
才能往前走下去
Just like you asked me,
就像你刚才问的一样
I asked myself every day
那时候我天天都在问自己
how I cut off the knot in my heart.
怎么斩自己的心
You did it, didn't you?
您做到了
Yes.
是的
By improving the sword intent of Snakes in Sleeves
只要将两袖青蛇的意境
to another level,
再上一层
I invented my real unique move.
才是我真正的绝学
It's called
它的名字
Open the Heaven's Gate.
叫作一剑开天门
I seemed to see something.
我好像隐约看到了什么
That's because I was influencing you with the true meaning
那是我用一剑开天门的真意
of Open the Heaven's Gate.
在影响你
What you saw
你看到的
was the secret of the move.
就是这一剑的秘密
You can show me a vision?
你能让我看到幻觉
When martial arts develop to perfection,
武功走到极致
they can influence you from body to heart.
从身到心
They can achieve many things
从改变现实到影响精神
from changing reality to affecting the spirit.
都是理所当然的
So
所以啊
some masters make you fear and shrink back
有些高手光站在那
only by standing there.
就让你恐惧退缩
It's because you're overwhelmed
本质原因就是因为他的精神
by their spirit.
压倒了你
Let's put it aside.
先不说这些
What have you seen just now?
你在恍惚中看到了些什么
I saw you splitting the sky.
看到一剑斩开天地
I don't understand.
我有些不太明白
What is heaven's mandate?
什么是天命
Heaven's mandate
天命者
is natural justice bestowed by natural law.
天道所赋之正理也
What is the way of heaven and man?
何为天人之道
A man should respect heaven's mandate.
君子当畏天命
If a man doesn't respect the heaven,
不畏敬天
the deepest disaster will befall the man,
其殃来至暗
which is invisible.
潜而无形
That's why
所以啊
the ancients said man must conform to the way of heaven.
古人说要顺应天道
Those who go along with it have good luck
顺者吉
and those who resist it have ill luck.
逆者凶
The way of heaven covers all living creatures.
天道覆盖众生
Man lives under heaven,
人伏于天穹之下
but eagers to be immortal.
渴望成就天人
Through Heaven's Gate,
而天门
man becomes immortal.
便是诸生成天人之路
Those who pass through the gate
过天门者
will lord it over all living creatures.
则可凌驾众生
But I refuse to accept it.
可我偏偏不服
Accept what?
不服什么
I refuse to accept that heaven decides man's life,
不服天道能定人生
man can't be the master of their own fate,
不服命运无法抗争
man can't conquer heaven,
不服人无法胜天
and immortals overrun all living beings.
不服天人便是仙神
I'll use my sword
我有我手中剑
to split Heaven's Gate.
斩开天门
All my life,
我李淳罡终此一生
I'll be a man who is dedicated
就是一个人
to exploring the way of heaven but not surrendering to it.
探索天道
I'll find my own way without fearing immortals.
寻自身路不畏天人
Even if all gods and demons come to earth,
就算古今神魔皆临凡尘
I'll kill them with my sword!
我李淳罡皆以一剑斩之
Now, do you understand
现在你明白
what Open the Heaven's Gate is?
什么是一剑开天门了吧
Defying fate
斩去天命
and cutting off the shackles,
斩去枷锁
with unyielding spirit,
我有这不屈在手
I'll get rid of all hesitation
便可斩去一切彷徨无措
and the fear in my heart,
斩去心中畏惧阴霾
thus, with a clear heart,
以此心澄澈
I'll cross the mortal world.
横渡凡尘
The idea
这念头
is the soul of Open the Heaven's Gate.
才是一剑开天门的魂魄所在
Did you master the move at that time?
当年您把一剑开天门练成了
I did.
练成了
How did you lose to Wang Xianzhi, then?
那你怎么可能输给王仙芝
During my fight against Wang Xianzhi,
与王仙芝那一战
I only used Snakes in Sleeves.
我只用了两袖青蛇
I didn't use Open the Heaven's Gate.
没用一剑开天门
Why?
为什么
Wang is a talent.
王仙芝天纵之才啊
I didn't want him to die.
我不想他就此陨落啊
So you'd rather lose to him?
那你宁愿自己输
I wasn't sure if I could win
当时如果我不杀他
without killing him.
我没把握赢
I hesitated a little.
我有点犹豫
The moment I hesitated while fighting Wang Xianzhi,
与王仙芝交手怎么可以犹豫呢
I lost.
当然就输了
You should have another fight.
那应该再打一场啊
I thought so, too.
本来我是这么想的
I wanted to improve my skills.
再磨磨剑意
When I got full control of the move,
让一剑开天门收发随心之后
I would have another fight against Wang Xianzhi.
再与王仙芝打一场
I might probably win him
那么大概就能既赢他
without killing him.
又不杀他
But the fight
但是这一场
has never come true.
始终没打成
Because soon after that,
因为在那之后不久
I lost my life.
我的人生就输了
My sword intent and battle intent
我的剑意和战意
were all gone.
全废了
How did you lose your life?
人生怎么输啊
You had mastered Open the Heaven's Gate.
你都练成一剑开天门了
People don't get everything
人不是武功高
or live a happy life
就能得到一切
just because they're masters of martial arts.
就能过好一生的
I killed
对我来说
the most important person to me
最重要的那个人
with my own hands.
被我亲手杀了
From that day on,
从那天起
nothing matters anymore.
什么都不重要了
You...
你
No matter what happened,
不管怎么说
it was all over.
都过去了
Your Highness.
世子
Mr. Li.
李前辈
We found a wooden box near the camp.
在营地旁捡到一个木盒子
Inside is the information
里面是当年王妃
about Her Grace's murder.
遇伏的消息
Let me see.
给我看看
No matter what you see,
不管是什么消息
don't forget the sword that cuts off the knot in your heart.
别忘了斩向内心枷锁那一剑
Open the Heaven's Gate.
一剑开天门
Isn't it
那不是传说中
Mr. Li's legendary ultimate sword move?
李前辈的最终剑术吗
Did he pass it on to you?
他传给你了
It's not a sword move.
那不是剑术
It's the true meaning.
是真意
True meaning?
真意
Wang Xianzhi was also in the capital that night.
王仙芝那一晚也出现在京城
Is he the murderer of my mother?
难不成是他对我娘出手
The origin of the box
这盒子
is unknown.
来路不明
It isn't necessarily true.
未必是真的
Do you know what the painting is?
你说这纸上画的是什么
It looks like
好像是
some doodles.
随意涂写的痕迹
It doesn't affect reading.
倒是不影响正文
Leave it alone.
先不管它